A Guide to the University of Connecticut, Committee of Five Records 1970.0002
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
University of Connecticut, Committee of Five Records
[1953]-1956
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1970.0002
0.25 Linear Feet
In March of 1953, a Committee of Five was appointed by the standing committee of the University Senate (acting at the request of the administration) to investigate the charge that four members of the faculty, Paul Zilsel, Robert Glass, Harold Lewis, and Emanuel Margolis, were communists. Committee members included Fred A. Cazel, Jr., Harold G. Halcrow, C. Albert Kind, Arthur L. Wood, and Marcel Kessel as Chairman. In a unanimous report, the committee recommended to the Board of Trustees that all four faculty members be retained at the University of Connecticut.
History
In March 1953, a Committee of Five was appointed by the standing committee of the University Senate (acting at the request of the administration) to investigate the charge that four members of the faculty, Paul Zilsel, Robert Glass, Harold Lewis, and Emanuel Margolis, were communists. Committee members included Fred A. Cazel, Jr., Harold G. Halcrow, C. Albert Kind, Arthur L. Wood, and Marcel Kessel as Chairman. In a unanimous report, the committee recommended to the Board of Trustees that all four faculty members be retained at the University of Connecticut.
Scope and Content
These records primarily contain minutes of the Committee's meetings and the final report.
Acquisition Information
These papers were donated by Marcel Kessel at an undetermined date.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Anti-communist movements; Communists; Administrative records; Education; United States (nation); Political participation; Connecticut (state); Communism; Academic freedom
- Series I: Committee Records, 1953-1954
  - Correspondence, 1953 March - 1954 April (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Minutes of meetings, 1953 March - 1953 June (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Glass, Robert, 1953, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lewis, Harold, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Margolis, Emanuel, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Zilsel, Paul, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - American Associations of University Professors, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - The Atlantic, vol. 191 no. 6, 1953 June (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Princeton Alumni Weekly, vol. LII no. 22, 1953 April 17 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Clippings, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series II: Report to the Board of Trustees of the University of Connecticut by the Committee of Five Investigating Charges of Communism Against Four Members of the Faculty, 1953
  - Draft pieces and notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Semi-final Draft, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Final Draft, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 5)